James Harold Doolittle Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
James Harold Doolittle Papers 1919-1990 (bulk 1940-1960)
MSS18754
Doolittle, James Harold, 1896-1993
33,000 items
110 containers plus 1 oversize
29.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
U.S. Air Force officer and U.S. Army officer. Correspondence, speeches, writings, reports, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, awards, maps, photographs, and other papers relating chiefly to Doolittle's service in the U.S. Air Force.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Arnold, Henry Harley, 1886-1950--Correspondence.; Chiang, May-ling Soong, 1897-2003--Correspondence.; Doolittle, James Harold, 1896-1993.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Halsey, William F. (William Frederick), 1882-1959--Correspondence.; King, Ernest Joseph, 1878-1956--Correspondence.; Magnolia, L. R.--Correspondence.; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959--Correspondence.; Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1885-1945--Correspondence.; Spaatz, Carl, 1891-1974--Correspondence.; Taylor, Maxwell D. (Maxwell Davenport), 1901-1987--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Air Force.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Japan.
Places
Tokyo (Japan)--History--Bombardment, 1942.
Occupations
Air Force officers.; Army officers.
Provenance
The papers of James Harold Doolittle, U.S Air Force officer and U.S. Army officer, were given to the Library of Congress by Doolittle in 1974. Additional material was given by Lee R. Magnolia from 1988 to 1990.
Transfers
Record albums have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of James Harold Doolittle are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1896, Dec. 14 Born, Alameda, Calif.
1916 Entered University of California, Berkeley, Calif.
1917 Flying cadet, United States Army Signal Corps Married Josephine Daniels (died 1988)
1918 Completed flight training and commissioned second lieutenant
1920 Regular commission and promoted to first lieutenant
1922 Bachelor of arts, University of California, Berkeley, Calif. First air crossing of the United States under twenty-four hours
1924 Masters of science, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Boston, Mass.
1925 Doctorate in aeronautical engineering, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Boston, Mass. Won Schneider Cup Race
1927 First flier to perform outside loop
1930 Resigned regular army commission Awarded Harmon Trophy Manager, Aviation Division, Shell Oil Co.
1931 Won Bendix Trophy Race from Burbank, Calif. to Cleveland, Ohio
1932 Won Thompson Trophy, Cleveland, Ohio
1940 President of the Institute of Aeronautical Sciences Returned to active duty, Army Air Corps
1942 Led sixteen B-25 bombers off deck of aircraft carrier in bombing raid over Japan Promoted to brigadier general Promoted to major general Awarded Congressional Medal of Honor
1943 1945 Commanded Twelfth Air Force in North Africa Commanded Fifteenth Air Force in Mediterranean theater Commanded Eighth Air Force in Europe and the Pacific
1946 Inactive reserve status
1946 1967 Vice president, Shell Oil Co.; later a director
1948 Awarded Silver Star
1951 Special assistant to chief of staff, Air Force
1959 Retired from the United States Air Force
1959 1963 Chairman of board of Space Technology Laboratories, Inc., Redondo Beach, Calif.
1983 Received United States Military Academy’s Sylvanus Thayer Award for distinguished military service
1985 Promoted to four star general
1989 Awarded Presidential Medal of Freedom
1993, Sept. 27 Died, Pebble Beach, Calif.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of James H. Doolittle (1896-1993) span the years 1919-1990, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1940-1960 and consisting of correspondence, speeches, writings, reports, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, awards, maps, photographs, and other papers relating chiefly to Doolittle's service in the United States Air Force. Doolittle had a long career as a civilian and military aviator, government official and adviser, and business executive, but he was most celebrated for directing and leading an air raid on Tokyo in the early months of World War II against Japan. The collection is organized into seven series: Correspondence File, General File, National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, Speeches and Articles, Miscellany, Addition, and Oversize.
Included in the collection are military records of Doolittle and a large amount of photographs and printed material. In general, the correspondence contains routine discussions of business matters, hunting trips, social affairs, and reunions of the American fliers who attacked Tokyo in April 1942. Materials relating to the raid include a map of Japan signed by some of the participants, telegrams from Generals George C. Marshall and Henry Harley Arnold, a handwritten memorandum from Admiral Ernest Joseph King, and letters of thanks and appreciation from Admiral William F. Halsey and May Ling-Soong Chiang. Additional correspondents from the war period include letters from Dwight D. Eisenhower, George S. Patton, Carl Spaatz, and Maxwell D. Taylor.
An addition to the papers includes correspondence, articles about Doolittle, and a photograph showing a formation of B-25s in dual mode. Most of the correspondence consists of short notes from Doolittle thanking Lee R. Magnolia for sending clippings related to aviation, aerospace, politics, whaling, and other topics.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in seven series:
Correspondence File, 1940-1959
General File, 1920-1970
National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, 1956-1958
Speeches and Articles, 1943-1956
Miscellany, 1919-1971
Addition, 1957-1990
Oversize
Container List
- Correspondence File, 1940-1959 (Box 1-4)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and therein chronologically.
  - "A" miscellaneous, 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - "B" miscellaneous, 1955-1958
  - "C" miscellaneous, 1955-1958
  - "D" miscellaneous, 1955-1958
  - "E" miscellaneous, 1940, 1956-1958
  - "F" miscellaneous, 1955-1958
  - "G" miscellaneous, 1955-1958
  - Guggenheim, Harry, 1955-1958 (Box 2)
  - "H" miscellaneous, 1955-1958
  - Hill, Walter, 1956-1958
  - "I" miscellaneous, 1958
  - "J" miscellaneous, 1955-1958
  - "K" miscellaneous, 1956-1958
  - Lovelace, Randolph, 1956-1958
  - "L" miscellaneous, 1956-1958
  - "M" miscellaneous, 1956-1958
  - "N" miscellaneous, 1956-1958 (Box 3)
  - Partridge, E. E., 1956-1958
  - "P" miscellaneous, 1955-1958
  - "Q" miscellaneous, 1958
  - "R" miscellaneous, 1956-1958
  - "S" miscellaneous, 1955-1959
  - "T" miscellaneous, 1956-1959
  - "U" miscellaneous, 1957-1959 (Box 4)
  - "V" miscellaneous, 1956-1959
  - "W" miscellaneous, 1955-1959
  - "X-Z" miscellaneous, 1956-1957
- General File, 1920-1970 (Box 4-36)
  Correspondence, memoranda, invitations, reports, lists, studies, printed matter, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged by subject or type of material.
  - Alaska trips-awards, 1955-1958 (Box 4)
  - Clubs
    - General, 1939, 1949-1958
    - Bohemian, 1958
    - Boone and Crockett, 1955-1958
    - Order of Daedalians, 1956-1959 (Box 5)
    - The Explorers Club, 1956-1958
    - Lotos Club, 1956-1958
    - National Aviation Club, 1956-1958
    - The Wings Club, 1956-1958
    - Quartet Club-Maine, 1956-1958
    - Shiners and masons, 1956-1958
    - Tokyo fliers, 1956-1958
    - Waterhen Lodge, 1956-1958
  - Collier Award committee, 1953-1958 (Box 6)
  - Dr. C. C. Criss Award, 1950-1956
  - Flight Safety Foundation, 1948-1958
  - Guggenheim awards, 1950-1958
  - Harmon Trophy awards, 1950-1958
  - J. C. Hunsaker Fund, 1956-1958
  - National Industrial Conference Board, 1956-1958
  - National Safety Council, 1956-1958
  - Red Cross, 1956-1958
  - Von Karman Institute, 1956-1958 (Box 7)
  - Wycombe Abbey Foundation, 1956-1958
  - Air University-Maxwell Air Force Base, 1956-1958
  - U. S. Air Force-general, 1956-195
  - Air Force-research and development, 1956-1958
  - Membership lists, 1956-1958 (Box 8)
  - Air Force-Scientific Advisory Board, 1956-1958
  - Aviation general, 1956-1958
  - Congress, 1956-1958
  - Defense Science Board, 1956-1958
  - Foreign intelligence activities, 1956-1958
  - Institute of Aeronautical Science, 1956-1958
  - Joint Civilian Orientation Conference, 1956-1959 (Box 9)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology
    - Correspondence, 1956-1958
    - Minutes, 1956-1958
    - Aeronautical engineering visiting committee, 1956-1958
    - Sponsored research visiting committee, 1956-1958
  - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (Box 10)
    - National Aeronautics and Space Act, 1958
    - General, 1956-1957, (2 folders)
  - National Air Museum-Smithsonian, 1956-1958 (Box 11)
  - Research-projects-studies funds, 1957-1958
  - Science Advisory Committee, 1955-1958
  - Security Resources Panel, 1957
  - Space Technology Laboratories, 1958
  - Stassen Disarmament Committee, 1956-1958
  - Stassen, Harold, report, 1955
  - Strategic Air Command tours, 1955-1958
  - Acceptances, 1956-1958
  - Itineraries, 1951-1958 (Box 12)
  - Literary efforts (others), 1956-1958
  - Luncheons-dinners-awards, 1957-1958
  - Requests: photographs, advice, autographs, testimonials, etc., 1956-1958
  - Television, 1956-1958
  - Coral Sea celebration, 1956, (4 folders); (1 folder) (Box 13, Box 14)
  - Department of Defense, electronic parts and tubes, 1958
  - Telegrams, 1956
  - Biography, 1940
  - Personal papers-military, 1946-1959, (2 folders)
  - Passports, 1950 (Box 15)
  - Biographical material, 1957
  - Cadillac, 1956-1958
  - Assignment as special assistant to the secretary and to chief of staff
    - 1952-1955
  - Scenario Doolittle movie
  - Reynold's book on Doolittle
  - Doolittle's life story, Collier's
  - Doolittle's flight record
  - Doolittle's military appointments, 1946-1947 (Box 16)
  - Official military correspondence, 1945-1948, (2 folders)
  - Recommendations for regular army commission, 1946
  - Reunion of 8th Air Force in England, 1947
  - Personal correspondence, special, 1943-1945
  - Miscellaneous letters, etc., 1933-1942
  - Military correspondence, 1920-1930 (Box 17)
  - Commanding general's reports, 1944-1945
  - Pilot handbooks, air force radio facility charts, installations, air route manuals, etc., 1943-1945
  - Bombardment planning, U.S. prior to joining 8th Air Force, England, 1942 (Box 18)
  - Bombing British by day, Japanese strategy, torpedo, etc. 1941-1942
  - Report on visit to England, 1941
  - Alaska, Adak, Marks Air Force Base, Ladd Air Force Base
  - Korea
  - 8th Air Force, Okinawa, 1945
  - North Africa
  - Operational file
    - 1945
    - 1944 (Box 19)
    - 1942-1943
  - Official entertainment voucher, 1944-1945
  - Songs, poems, etc., 1943-1951
  - Signal Corps property, 1940
  - Property, army, accountable, 1942
  - Tokyo fliers, correspondence, 1955
  - Tokyo fliers (Box 20)
  - Tokyo raiders meeting, Galveston, Tex., 1949
  - Tokyo fliers, 1947-1948
  - Tokyo fliers party
    - 1948
    - 1947
  - Tokyo flight matters
  - Tokyo fliers, 1946
  - Tokyo fliers, Miami, Fla., 1946 (Box 21)
  - Material on Tokyo raid
  - Report on aerial bombing of Tokyo, 1942
  - Crew reports, 1942, (2 items); (2 unlabeled folders and 4 items); (1 item) (Box 22, Box 23)
  - Speeches after Tokyo
  - Personal
    - A, 1946-1955
    - B, 1948-1955
    - C, 1949-1955
    - D, 1947-1955 (Box 24)
    - E, 1949-1955
    - F, 1949-1955
    - G, 1949-1955
    - H, 1948-1955 (Box 25)
    - I, 1953-1955
    - J, 1948-1955
    - K, 1947-1955
    - L, 1949-1955
    - M, 1948-1955 (Box 26)
    - N, 1949-1955
    - O, 1949-1955
    - P, 1948-1955
    - Q, 1955
    - R, 1947-1955
    - S, 1946-1955 (Box 27)
    - T, 1949-1955
    - U, 1953-1955
    - V, 1949-1955
    - W, 1949-1955
    - X, Y, Z, 1949-1955
  - Air Force correspondence, Washington, D.C., office (Box 28)
  - Air Force Historical Society
  - Air Board
  - Air Force Association, 1946-1958
  - Air Force Scientific Advisory Board
  - Acceptances, 1955 (Box 29)
  - Arnold Air Society
  - Air Research and Development Command
  - Berlin airlift
  - Brayton
  - Civilian advisory committee
  - Lionel Curtis
  - Commission on the National Security Organization (Box 30)
  - Congressional Air Policy Board
  - Civil defense
  - Active tour of duty, 1955
  - Northeast Air Command, 1954
  - Cleveland, Ohio, national air races, 1932
  - Doolittle, Missouri
  - Eisenhower-Nixon campaign
  - English Speaking Union (Fellowship of United States and British Comrades)
  - Henry Ford, Chairman National Conference of Christians and Jews (Box 31)
  - 1st Army Advisory Committee for Greater New York
  - 50th anniversary of powered flight
  - Fred Herman Brooks Scholarship
  - Walter Hill, 1946-1955
  - Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences, 1941-1955
  - Joint Civilian Orientation Conference, 1955
  - Miscellaneous speeches and articles, 1943
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, financing plan (Box 32)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1948-1956
  - Military fuel requirements
  - President's Airport Commission
  - Retirement age study (Box 33)
  - Frank Whittle
  - Waterhen Lodge
    - 1948-1951
    - 1952-1953
  - Wings Club, 1955
  - New York City Airport Authority material
  - Doolittle's statement before Senate Military Affair Committee
  - Army Caste Board, report and correspondence (Box 34)
  - Tokyo raiders reunions (Box 35)
    - 1959
    - 1960
    - 1961
    - 1962
    - 1963
    - 1964
    - 1965
    - 1966
    - 1967, (2 folders) (Box 36)
    - 1968
    - 1969
    - 1970
- National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, 1956-1958 (Box 37)
  Meeting reports and minutes.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1956-1958 (Box 37)
- Speeches and Articles, 1943-1956 (Box 38-40)
  Copies of speeches and articles and related source material.
  Arranged chronologically with note cards filed at the end of the series.
  - 1943-1944 (Box 38)
  - 1945, (2 folders)
  - 1947
  - 1948
  - 1949
  - 1950 (Box 39)
  - 1952
  - 1953
  - 1954
  - 1955
  - 1956 (Box 40)
  - Undated speeches and source material
  - 8th Air Force note cards
- Miscellany, 1919-1971 (Box 41-109)
  Correspondence, reports, speeches and writings, photographs and photographs albums, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, magazines, pamphlets and brochures, and other miscellany.
  Arranged by type of material or subject.
  - Doolittle's doctoral thesis, 1925 (Box 41)
  - Reports relating to raid
  - Loose newspapers (3 items)
  - Steel cut for newspaper reproduction
  - Australia, 1956 (3 items) (Box 42)
  - Reports, 1942, 1957 (2 items)
  - Stassen disarmament air inspection, 1956-1959
  - Tokyo raiders' war fate, 1942-1947
  - Reports, 1954-1957 (4 items) (Box 43)
  - Speeches, Doolittle and others, 1957-1959 (4 items)
  - Stassen committee, 1955-1957
  - Autobiography, incomplete (Box 44)
  - Speeches by Doolittle, 1951
  - Wings Club, 1950-1954
  - Job lists, 1955-1958 (Box 45)
  - Links Club dinner, 1952
  - Pistol licenses, 1948-1955
  - Records, Gee-Bee monoplane, 1932
  - Schneider seaplane race, 1925
  - Trips and tours
    - Air Force Research and Development Command, Korean tour, 1952
    - Far East trip, 1950
    - Shell U.S. Tour, 1952
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 46)
    - 1953
      - Apr.-June
      - July
      - Aug.
      - Sept.
      - Oct.
      - Nov.
      - Dec.
    - 1954
      - Jan.
      - Feb.
      - Mar.
      - Apr., (2 folders) (Box 47)
      - May
      - July
      - Aug.
      - Sept.
      - Oct. (Box 48)
      - Nov.
      - Dec.
    - 1955 (Box 49)
      - Jan.
      - Feb.
      - Mar.
      - Apr.
      - May
      - June (Box 50)
      - July
      - Aug.
      - Sept.
      - Oct.
      - Nov. (Box 51)
      - Dec.
    - 1956
      - Jan
      - Feb.
      - Mar.
  - Clippings on Tokyo bombing, 1942 (Box 52)
  - Correspondence
    - 1930
    - 1942
  - Photograph albums (Box 53)
    - 1947-1968, (10 vols.)
    - 1964-1966, undated, (7 vols.) (Box 54)
    - 1955-1956, undated, (6 vols.) (Box 55)
    - 1959, undated, (5 vols.) (Box 56)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 57)
    - Gourmet
      - 1950-1951
      - 1952-1953 (Box 58)
      - 1954-1955 (Box 59)
    - Sunset, 1952-1955 (Box 60)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1950
  - Retired air force officers and widows, 1950-1951 (Box 61)
  - Good Housekeeping, undated
  - Interview, 1960
  - Magazine, food articles, untitled and undated (Box 62)
  - Tokyo raiders reunion, 1967 (Box 63)
  - Good Housekeeping, undated (Box 64)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 65)
    - 1945
    - 1950-1953 (Box 66)
    - 1946-1949 (Box 67)
  - Woman's Home Companion, 1952-1954 (Box 68)
  - Ladies's Home Journal (Box 69)
    - 1942-1945
    - 1952-1954 (Box 70)
  - American Home, 1942-1949 (Box 71)
  - Ladies's Home Journal, 1949-1951 (Box 72)
  - Words to Live By and similar columns, 1947, undated (Box 73)
  - Illustrations from magazines, undated (Box 74)
  - Magazine articles and newspaper clippings, 1949-1955 (Box 75)
  - Magazine covers, articles, illustrations, 1919-1952 (Box 76)
  - Printed matter, 1925-1955 (Box 77)
  - Woman's Home Companion, 1951-1954 (Box 78)
  - Newspaper clippings and other, 1942-1955 (Box 79)
  - Newspaper clippings, printed matter, and correspondence, 1919-1948 (Box 80)
  - Radio script, speeches, and other material, 1942-1944 (Box 81)
  - Wright Day dinner, 1952 (Box 82)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 83)
    - 1942
    - 1942 (Box 84)
  - Air Force Association, 1946-1950 (Box 85)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 86)
    - 1925-1931
    - 1931-1932 (Box 87)
  - Pike's Peak monument, 1953 (Box 88)
  - Woman's Home Companion, 1942-1949 (Box 89)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1940-1944 (Box 90)
  - McCall's (Box 91)
    - 1951-1952
    - 1947-1954 (Box 92)
  - Panama trip, 1968 (Box 93)
  - Australian trip, 1956 (Box 94)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1927-1928 (Box 95)
  - The Doolittles in World War II, 1942-1944 (Box 96)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 97)
    - 1925-1926
    - 1933, 1940-1943 (Box 98)
    - 1940-1943 (Box 99)
  - Printed matter (Box 100)
    - 1946-1954
    - 1929-1953 (Box 101)
    - 1919-1950 (Box 102)
  - Newspaper clippings, correspondence, 1919-1926 (Box 103)
  - Army-Navy Production Award, 1943 (Box 104)
  - National Aviation Hall of Fame etchings, artwork, awards, and photographs, 1942-1971 See also Oversize (Box 105)
  - Ladies's Home Journal, 1947-1955 (Box 106)
  - Better Homes and Gardens, 1951-1954 (Box 107)
  - Printed matter (Box 108)
    - 1905-1951
    - 1942-1953 (Box 109)
- Addition, 1957-1990 (Box 110)
  Correspondence, articles about Doolittle, and photograph.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Articles about Doolittle, 1985-1990 (Box 110)
  - Correpondence to Lee R. Magnolia, 1971-1984 (Box 110)
  - Photograph of B-25s, 1957, 1990 (Box 110)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  An award.
  Arranged and described according to the container from which it was removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Awards (Container 105)